[
    {
        "question": "Se abbod grete þone (<em>cyning</em>) #### — The abbot greets the king",
        "correctAnswer": "cyning",
        "explanation":"Here 'cyning' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'grete', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen sloh þone (<em>biscop</em>) #### in þæm tune — The thane slew the bishop in the town",
        "correctAnswer": "biscop",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'sloh', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða biscopas geaf þone (<em>stan</em>) #### to þæm þegne — The bishops gave the stone to the thane",
        "correctAnswer": "stan",
        "explanation":"Here 'stan' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ond seo cwen gretaþ þa (<em>biscop</em>) #### — The king and the queen greet the bishops",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopas",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is plural and directly receiving the action of the verb 'grete', so it takes the plural accusative 'as' ending to become 'biscopas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning sloh þa (<em>þegen</em>) #### — The king slew the thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnas|þegenas",
        "explanation":"Here 'þegen' is plural and directly receiving the action of the verb 'sloh', so it takes the plural accusative 'as' ending to become 'þegnas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen geaf þa (<em>gar</em>) #### to þaem cyninge — The thane gives the spears to the king",
        "correctAnswer": "garas",
        "explanation":"Here 'gar' is plural and directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it takes the plural accusative 'as' ending to become 'garas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "To þæm biscop geaf se cyning þa (<em>beag</em>) #### — The king gave rings to the bishop",
        "correctAnswer": "beagas",
        "explanation":"Here 'beag' is plural and directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it takes the plural accusative 'as' ending to become 'beagas'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "To þæm (<em>cyning</em>) #### geaf se biscop beag — To the king, the bishop gave a ring",
        "correctAnswer": "cyninge",
        "explanation":"Here 'cyning' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending to become 'cyninge'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "cyning",
                "explanation": "Cyning is the nominative or accusative singular form of the word. Here 'cyning' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending to become 'cyninge'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen ferþ to þæm (<em>biscop</em>) #### mid wordum fram þæm cyning — The thane goes to the bishop with words from the king",
        "correctAnswer": "biscope",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it takes the singular dative 'e' ending to become 'biscope'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "biscop",
                "explanation": "Biscop is the nominative or accusative singular form of the word. Here 'biscop' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending."
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se biscop ferde fram þæm (<em>þegen</em>) #### to þæm cyning — The bishop went from the thane to the king",
        "correctAnswer": "þegne|þegene",
        "explanation":"Here 'þegen' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it takes the singular dative 'e' ending to become 'þegne'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þis daeg, Æðelred cyning ferde to þæm (<em>tun</em>) #### mid his broðor — On this day, King Ethelred went to the town with his brother",
        "correctAnswer": "tune",
        "explanation":"Here 'tun' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it takes the singular dative 'e' ending to become 'tune'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ferþ to þæm (<em>beorg</em>) #### — The king goes to the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "beorgum",
        "explanation":"Here 'beorg' is plural and not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it takes the plural dative 'um' ending to become 'beorgum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wærferhþ biscop ferde to þæm (<em>biscop</em>) #### in Lundene ond Wiltunscire — Bishop Warfehth went to the bishops of London and Wiltshire",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopum",
        "explanation":"Here 'biscop' is plural and not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it takes the plural dative 'um' ending to become 'biscopum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He geaf þa garas to þæm (<em>þegen</em>) #### — He gave the spears to the thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnum|þegenum",
        "explanation":"Here 'þegen' is plural and not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it takes the plural dative 'um' ending to become 'þegnum'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se abbot com fram þæm (<em>beorg</em>) ####⁠ — The abbot came from the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "beorgum",
        "explanation":"Here 'beorg' is plural and not directly receiving the action of the verb 'com', so it takes the plural dative 'um' ending to become 'beorgum'",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se biscop ferþ to þæm halige (<em>stede</em>) ####⁠ — The bishop goes to the holy place",
        "correctAnswer": "stede",
        "explanation":"Here 'stede' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it should take the singular dative 'e', but since it already ends in 'e' no additional letters are added",        
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
            "incorrectAnswer": "stedee",
            "explanation":"While 'stede' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ' and so is dative singular, it already ends in e, so no additional letters are added"        
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie þreowon þa (<em>gar</em>) #### to þæm wicingum⁠ — They threw the spears at the vikings",
        "correctAnswer": "garas",
        "explanation":"Here 'gar' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'þreowon', so it takes the plural accusative 'as' ending to become 'garas'",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He æt þone (<em>fugol</em>) ####⁠ — He ate the bird",
        "correctAnswer": "fugol",
        "explanation":"Here 'fugol' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'æt', so it is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða biscopas comon fram þæm (<em>tun</em>) #### Londenum ond Readingum genemned — The bishops came from the towns called London and Reading",
        "correctAnswer": "tunum",
        "explanation":"Here 'tun' is plural and not directly receiving the action of the verb 'comon', so takes the plural dative 'um' ending to become 'tunum'",        
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]